A Guide to the William J. Alford, Jr., Papers, 1951-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
William J. Alford, Jr., Papers, 1951-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1987-007
0.6 cu. ft. 2 boxes
Spanning from 1951-1988, the William J. Alford, Jr., Papers contains NACA and NASA research memoranda and reports; publication drafts; a Langley working paper with associated research notes and patent details; correspondence; award certificates; AIAA (American Institute of Aeronautics & Astronautics) conference programs; and personnel papers pertaining to William J. Alford's career as an aeronautical engineer. A detailed schematic drawing of "the variable sweep wing configuration tested in the high-speed 7- by 10- foot tunnel" is also included.
Alford, William J., Jr., 1924-2010
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to Special Collections in 1987.
Biographical Note
William J. Alford, Jr. (1924-2010) graduated from Granby High School in 1942. During WWII he served in the United States Marine Corps as a dive-bomber pilot. In June 1949, Alford graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI) with a Bachelor of Science in Aeronautical Engineering. He continued graduate work in Aerospace Engineering at VPI from 1959-1960. He worked as an engineer at NACA-NASA Langley (1949-1980), served as head of the Advanced Transport Technology Program (1970-1975), and held the position of manager of the Energy Efficient Transport Office (1976-1979). Alford also served as the head of the Advanced Military Technology Office (1979-1980). Alford also holds co-ownership with Edward C. Polhamus of the patent for the Variable Sweep Wing Configuration (1962).
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains NACA and NASA research memoranda and reports, publication drafts, research notes and patent details for the variable-sweep wing design, correspondence, award certificates, AIAA (American Institute of Aeronautics & Astronautics) conference programs, and personnel file papers pertaining to William J. Alford's career as an aeronautical engineer. Also included are a Langley working paper, with associated variable-sweep research notes and patent details, and a detailed schematic drawing, of "the variable sweep wing configuration tested in the high-speed 7- by 10- foot tunnel." These materials date from 1951 to 1988.
Some related materials may appear in separate folders. For example, awards and correspondence are also included in the biographical and career information file. Additionally, some personnel file papers, especially many of those in the biographical and career information file, contain photocopies in the place of the original documents.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, Series I: Papers and Series II: Publications.
Series I contains papers that date from 1958 to 1988. This series includes award certificates, correspondence, personnel file papers, conference programs, and research notes and material related to the variable-sweep wing patent. Some papers relating to Alford's career had been previously arranged; these materials and their ordering are maintained in the "Biographical and Career Information" file.
This series is arranged by material type.
Series II is comprised of NACA, NASA, RAND, United States Air Force Project RAND, NATO Advisory Group for Aeronautical Research and Development, and NASP publications. These documents range from 1951 to 1987. NACA and NASA publications form the majority of this series. Most publications list Alford as an author.
This series is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
For more information relating to Edward C. Polhamus and the variable-sweep wing patent see the Edward C. Polhamus Papers, Ms1990-051. Finding aid available online.
Index Terms
Persons:
Polhamus, Edward C., (Edward Charles), 1923-2001
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology; University Archives; University History
Occupations:
Aeronautical engineers.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers, 1958-1988
  - Biographical and Career Information, 1960-1974 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Award Certificates, 1979 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1988 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Variable-Sweep Research and Patent, 1958-1966 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Conference Programs, 1983 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1964-1980 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Series II: Publications, 1951-1987
  - NACA Publications, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 1-7)
    Bibliography
    Spreemann, Kenneth P., and Alford, William J., Jr.: Investigation of the Effects of Geometric Changes in an Underwing Pylon-Suspended External-Store Installation on the Aerodynamic Characteristics of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing at High Subsonic Speeds. NACA RM L50L12, 1951.
    Spreemann, Kenneth P., and Alford, William J., Jr.: Investigation of the Effects of Twist and Camber on the Aerodynamic Characteristics of a 50 Degree 38' Sweptback Wing of Aspect Ratio 2.98. Transonic-Bump Method. NACA RM L51C16, 1951.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and Byrnes, Andrew L., Jr.: Small-Scale Transonic Investigation of the Effects of Partial-Span Leading-Edge Camber on the Aerodynamic Characteristics of a 50 Degree 38' Sweptback Wing of Aspect Ratio 2.98. NACA RM L52D08a, 1952.
  - NACA Publications, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 1-8)
    Spreemann, Kenneth P., and Alford, William J., Jr.: Small-Scale Transonic Investigation of the Effects of Full-Span and Partial-Span Leading-Edge Flaps on the Aerodynamic Characteristics of a 50 Degree 38' Sweptback Wing of Aspect Ratio 2.98. NACA RM L52E12, 1952.
    Alford, William J., Jr.: Wind-Tunnel Investigation of the Static Longitudinal Stability Characteristics of a 0.15-Scale Model of the Hermes A-1E2 Missile at High Subsonic Mach Numbers. NACA RM SL52I10, 1952.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and Spreemann, Kenneth P.: Small-Scale Transonic Investigation of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing of Aspect Ratio 4 with Combinations of Nose-Flap Deflections and Wing Twist. NACA RM L52K13, 1953.
    Spreemann, Kenneth P., and Alford, William J., Jr.: Investigation of the Effects of Leading-Edge Chord-Extensions and Fences in Combination with Leading-Edge Flaps on the Aerodynamic Characteristics at Mach Numbers from 0.40 to 0.93 of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing of Aspect Ratio 4. NACA RM L53A09a, 1953.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and Pasteur, Thomas B., Jr.: The Effects of Changes in Aspect Ratio and Tail Height on the Longitudinal Stability Characteristics at High Subsonic Speeds of a Model with a Wing Having 32.6 Degrees Sweepback. NACA RM L53L09, 1954.
  - NACA Publications, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1-9)
    Silvers, H. Norman, King, Thomas J., Jr., and Alford, William J.: Wind-Tunnel Investigation at High Subsonic Speeds of the Effects of Wing-Mounted External Stores on the Loading and Aerodynamic Characteristics in Pitch of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing Combined with a Fuselage. NACA RM L54A21, 1954.
    Silvers, H. Norman, and Alford, William J., Jr.: Investigation at High Subsonic Speeds of the Effect of Adding Various Combinations of Missiles on the Aerodynamic Characteristics of Sweptback and Unswept Wings Combined with a Fuselage. NACA RM L54D20, 1954.
    Alford, William J., Jr.: Experimental Static Aerodynamic Forces and Moments at Low Speed on a Canard Missile during Simulated Launching from the Midsemispan and Wing-Tip Locations of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing-Fuselage Combination. NACA RM L55A12, 1955.
    Sleeman, William C., Jr., and Alford, William J., Jr.: Low-Speed Investigation of the Effects of Wing Tanks and Speed Brakes on the Static Stability of a Model Having a 40 Degree Swept Wing. NACA RM L55C17, 1955.
  - NACA Publications, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 1-10)
    Alford, William J., Jr., Silvers, H. Norman, and King, Thomas J., Jr.: Experimental Static Aerodynamic Forces and Moments at Low Speed on a Missile Model During Simulated Launching from the 25-Percent-Semispan and Wing-Tip Locations of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing-Fuselage Combination. NACA RM L55D20, 1955.
    Alford, William J., Jr.: Theoretical and Experimental Investigation of the Subsonic-Flow Fields Beneath Swept and Unswept Wings with Tables of Vortex-Induced Velocities. NACA TN 3738.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and King, Thomas J., Jr.: Experimental Static Aerodynamic Forces and Moments at High Subsonic Speeds on a Missile Model during Simulated Launching from the Midsemispan Location of a 45 Degree Sweptback Wing-Fuselage-Pylan Combination. NACA RM L56J05, 1957.
  - NACA Publications, 1957 (Box-folder 2-1)
    Alford, William J., Jr., and King, Thomas J., Jr.: Experimental Investigation of Flow Fields at Zero Sideslip Near Swept- and Unswept-Wing-Fuselage Combinations at Low Speed. NACA RM L56J19, 1957.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and King, Thomas J., Jr.: Experimental Static Aerodynamic Forces and Moments at High Subsonic Speeds on a Missile Model During Simulated Launching from Unswept-, Sweptback-, and Modified-Delta-Wing-Fuselage Combinations at Zero Sideslip. NACA RM L57B04, 1957.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and King, Thomas J., Jr.: Experimental Investigation of Effects of Moderate Sideslip on the Flow Fields Near a 45 Degree Swept-Wing-Fuselage Combination at Low Speed. NACA RM L57E10, 1957.
  - NASA Publications, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2-2)
    Alford, William J., Jr.: Some Effects of Horizontal-Tail Position on the Vertical-Tail Pressure Distributions of a Complete Model in Sideslip at High Subsonic Speeds. NASA Memo. 10-5-58L, 1958.
    Alford, William J., Jr., and Henderson, William P.: An Exploratory Investigation of the Low-Speed Aerodynamic Characteristics of Variable-Wing-Sweep Airplane Configurations. NASA TM X-142, 1959.
    Bielat, Ralph P., Robins, A. Warner, and Alford, William J., Jr.: The Transonic Aerodynamic Characteristics of Two Variable-Sweep Airplane Configurations Capable of Low-Level Supersonic Attack. NASA TM X-304, 1960.
  - NASA Publications, 1960-1981 (Box-folder 2-3)
    Bielat, Ralph P., and Pierpont, P. Kenneth: Transonic Aerodynamic Characteristics of a Variable-Sweep Airplane Configuration Having a 12-Percent-Thick Wing and an Inboard Pivot Location. NASA TM X-429, 1960.
    Alford, William J., Jr.: Subsonic Wind-Tunnel Investigation of Errors Indicated by Total-Pressure Tubes in the Flow Field of a Body Simulating the Nose of the X-15 Research Airplane. NASA TN D-1250, 1962.
    Nicks, Oran W., Whitehead, Allen H., and Alford, William J., Jr.: An Outlook for Cargo Aircraft of the Future. NASA TM X-72796, 1975.
    Polhamus, Edward C., and Toll, Thomas A.: Research Related to Variable Sweep Aircraft Development. NASA TM 83121, 1981.
  - Other Publications, 1963-1987 (Box-folder 2-4)
    Toll, T. A., Polhamus, E. C., and Aiken, W. S., Jr.: NASA Variable-Geometry Research. NATO: Advisory Group for Aeronautical Research and Development Report 447, 1963.
    Perry, Robert L.: Innovation and Military Requirements: A Comparative Study. RAND RM-5182-PR, 1967.
    Reed, Wilmer H., III., Hanson, Perry W., and Alford, W. J., Jr.: Assessment of Flutter Model Testing Relating to the National Aero-Space Plane. NASP Contractor Report 1002, 1987.